hello I'm your host David Barnard and my
guest today is Patrick Fen co-founder of
the app shop helping companies of all
sizes build grow and monetize
exceptional apps on the podcast I talked
with Patrick about estimating the
revenue potential of an app crafting an
exit strategy and why LTV is such a
terrible
metric hey Patrick thanks so much for
joining me on the podcast today thank
you for having me big fan of the podcast
and big big fan of Revenue cat yeah
super excited to have you on the podcast
and I wanted to kick things off talking
about your time at mosaic I think that's
a good framing it's kind of where you
learned the ropes as far as subscription
app businesses go and Mosaic did a lot
of really interesting stuff and built a
pretty great business famously recently
got sold off to bending spoons but I
wanted to talk a little bit about your
experience there kind of what brought
you there and what your role was as
context for what we're going to talk
about throughout the rest of the podcast
episode
yeah the brief background of me is my
career has been roughly split between
investing and operating roles and Mosaic
was actually the place where I made that
transition I got introduced to Mosaic
when it was actually just appal on back
in the day for folks familiar with that
brand appon had B really early to the
mobile app ecosystem our parent company
it was company called IAC had acquired
them when everything was still paid
downloads and so appon we owned it when
it went through that transition from
Paid downloads to subscriptions and we
saw phenomenal growth and a ton of
opportunity on the other side of that
and this was at a time when I was still
doing mergers and Acquisitions for IAC
while I was on the team I got introduced
to the appon team they had a big Vision
they felt like they really unlocked
something special in terms of
understanding and being able to
capitalize on that inapp subscription
opportunity and wanted to go out and
build a big portfolio of other apps and
other app developers so I originally
came in to help them execute on that
from an m&a perspective first through
the Acquisitions of itranslate and
teltec it translate being the developers
of itranslate teltech the developers of
robokiller plus some others but
robokiller was the flagship product
there and then a number of other smaller
deals on the other side of that so I got
involved in Mosaic and then within a
couple years I actually ended up running
both it translate and teltech as the
general manager of those two businesses
while still doing the m& for Mosaic so I
got to see the landscape I think from a
couple different lenses one both from
the investing and the operating side
over a multi-year period and then also
really got to ride that growth of the
mobile app industry again like we were
pretty early to subscribe and when there
was kind of like just infinite growth it
felt like in those early days all the
way to through to now where I think it's
a much more mature ecosystem everyone's
on subscriptions there's a lot more
defined best practices around how to do
it I and frankly I also think in some
ways growth is maybe harder than it used
to be and it takes more execution than
it used to so it's been a really fun
journey and all I would say is that
Mosaic we do feel like we accomplished a
lot we felt like we built one of the
leading portfolios in the space had a
great exit to bending spoons hope they
do well with the portfolio on the other
side of it it I'm and excited for what
comes next yeah it must have been a
fascinating time going from that single
kind of portfolio of apps with appal on
to then acquiring and getting to kind of
peek inside a lot of app businesses in
the m&a role and then actually become an
operator over teltech which I know rer
killer was one of the kind of Flagship
apps of the Mosaic portfolio while still
doing additional m&a along the way so
it's like you were both kind of seeing
what was going on and inside these other
businesses that Mosaic might want to buy
but then also like implementing those
strategies within the existing portfolio
company so you just have such a unique
perspective and again that's why I think
it it's going to be a really fascinating
chat today to kind of learn from those
experiences you know kind of one of the
top and one of the early movers in this
subscription app space so the first
thing I wanted to talk about is Market
sizing and this is something you must
have thought a lot about when you had
your m&a hat on was how big is this
Market going to be for this app you know
how much can we afford to pay how much
do we think this is going to grow
because you know famously Mosaic didn't
just buy up a bunch of apps like there's
a lot of companies now that'll just buy
any app that's doing you know 10K a
month 100K a month and it seems like
there's not as focused a strategy but
with Mosaic there was it seems like a
lot more thoughtful approach to like
trying to buy apps that could be big and
then the other thing I imagine as
general manager at rubber killer then
you also had to think about like what's
the opportunity of any new feature we
build and those are probably two very
similar problem spaces to think about
like we have this existing app that has
a market cap is this secondary product
Market fit should this be a new app and
there there's so much intertwined with
those two so I want to kind of lump
those together let's kick it off like
how did you think about in acquiring a
new app or going into a new line of
business like how to really understand
that potential t for that app yeah yeah
so we did think about it across a couple
different lenses so one was just Market
size um you are right we went for depth
so we needed to believe that you could
have a product that did tens of millions
of dollars of Revenue was kind of a
rough Benchmark we had for ourselves the
main reason we did that and I I think
one of the challenges when you go more
Downstream than that is you can easily
end up with a portfolio of like 50 to
100 apps that each do you know a couple
hundred, of Revenue and your overall p&l
looks good but it is really complex
managing that many apps one and two what
it probably means is you're very rarely
actually investing in each of those apps
maybe there's a couple you do but you
have this long taale of kind of like
Zombie products where they're making
revenue for for you and maybe that makes
Financial sense but it was hard for us
to justify that we were truly satisfying
those users or providing value on the
other side of that and that's why we
tried to shy away from that and really
wanted to buy products where we felt
like or build products where we felt
like this was an enduring product an
enduring category we can invest in it
and actually provide value to users on
an ongoing basis and be rewarded for
that so we did look for depth now on the
flip side of that I do think there's a
double-edged sort on your Tam where I
could also think about like you should
think about how big do you really want
to play in because it gets into the
second lens which is competition and
typically the bigger markets are going
to have more competition and you have to
think about how you how you think about
those trade-offs between those two
things meaning a big Market is great
only if you can take a substantial share
of that market or a specific share of
that market if is so competitive that
you can't actually Garner market share
it's not actually valuable to you so we
thought about size and competition as a
balance between each other and I think
there's a little bit of like a
Goldilocks approach you can take to
those things of markets that are big
enough to create enduring products and
businesses but you could still be maybe
a relative big fish in a smaller Pond
and that's not necessarily a terrible
place for you to play do you have some
concrete examples of like I mean let's
take ROK Killer maybe as an example of
something that Mosaic did buy so what
was a thought there on like how big that
market was and the thesis behind playing
in that market versus and then maybe an
example of a market that was maybe too
competitive where you're where you
looked at an acquisition and felt like
this is too big of space to compete in
yeah so the r example the basic thesis
there is it's a broadly applicable
product everyone get spam calls or spam
texts to a degree there are certain
demographics that care more about
solving that problem than others but we
got comfortable that it was a broadly
appearing appealing product that could
generate again tens of millions of
dollars of Revenue and then we looked at
the competitive landscape and robokiller
was the leader you had carriers are
somewhat relevant here but they're not
really invested in solving the solution
for a variety of reasons that are
probably more of a rabbit hole than
worth getting into here so we looked at
this is a problem that needs to be
solved by independent tools this is the
leading independent tool there aren't
major players entering this space from
adjacent categories so again good
good competitive Dynamics I think one
you can think about in the other
direction categories that we never got
in ourselves two examples that come to
mind are vpns VPN is a massive category
but there's also already a lot of people
making a lot of money there so if you
want to enter that category you have to
be prepared to spend a lot of money on
user acquisition to be able to Garner
market share because everyone else is
spending a lot of money on user
acquisition and if you don't play that
game there is no game to play so that
was one we shied away from because we
said the uni economics are not going to
makes sense for us long term we have to
be so reliant on aggressive paid
marketing slightly different lens but
similar rationale is we never got into
personal budgeting or Finance for a
similar but slightly different reason in
the sense that we thought the adjacent
competitors in Banks and more
traditional financial institutions made
that challenging long term because
similarly when you go out to acquire
users if you think about like what
you're actually acquiring them for
you're acquiring them for financial
management or budgeting or like their
money and how should they manage that
those are the same desires and
objectives and keywords to be like very
tactical that like a bank would
potentially want to acquire that
customer for and the bank is is going to
have a much much higher LTV than you are
ever going to have on your budgeting app
and so like you will always lose that
battle because they'll always be willing
to pay more for that customer than you
so again that was when we looked at and
said there's a lot of interesting things
in the category a lot of interesting
features that make those products
attractive but we don't think we can
effectively compete there in the long
term ter because it is such a big and
attractive Market because the ltbs can
be so high if you actually provide the
financial services which is not
something we're ever going to do yeah I
know that makes a ton of sense and then
you had a followup I kind of interrupted
you but I appreciate the kind of like
concrete examples and I think again
super helpful for folks to think about
as they're thinking about growing their
business and those same competitive
Dynamics I mean you know I know folks in
the meditation space and the language
learning space and it's like yeah those
are big spaces but it's important to
understand those competitive Dynamics
and understand the challenges you're
going to face along the way butow you
had more to say one point on that I'd
say is in those spaces I think there is
an argument for if you're bringing
something truly new and Innovative to
the table like the whole like are you
10x better than the current Solutions
not to say you shouldn't try but that
just being 10x better doesn't solve all
those Dynamics meaning like you still
have to get your product in the hands of
users and let them see that you're 10x
better so you still need to have a
strategy for how you going to do that
user acquisition if everyone's already
doing paid and they're already gobbling
up that top of the funnel and then the
third lens I was going to add is we
thought a lot about are we tapping into
existing demand or do we have to go out
and build a new product category not to
say one is always going to be better
than the other they're just different
and they have different different
Capital requirements so the way we
thought about it was if you're tapping
into existing demand you're probably
going to have more competition up front
but it's typically a lower capital
investment because you can start doing
things like Performance Marketing right
away or ASO right away and start getting
users in in a relatively profitable or
rational way if you have to go out and
build a new category people don't know
this product exists you're the first to
Market you have to build demand for it
you're probably running at a loss for
some period of time while you go out and
do that and so you need to factor that
into your thinking of can I do that and
am I willing to do that so I think
particularly for independent app
developers one thing I talk to
developers a lot about is like that's a
really great idea and that's really
exciting like do you have the resources
to see it through and scale it on the
other side of that though I think that's
how you should think about it yeah and
then how did you apply that thinking how
do you today apply that thinking when it
comes to building new features I mean
this is something where folks maybe
aren't always strategic enough it's like
ah we'll build this new feature because
it's cool but like then I imagine
there's some thought that should go into
is this a secondary product Market fit
is there a keyword that this feature is
going to allow us to compete on that
we're not comp on currently or like what
was the the kind of strategic thinking
behind expanding feature sets and
secondary product Market fit and then
even where like where maybe spinning up
a new app was a better solution than
kind of adding features to an existing
app yeah so I think you hit on all the
main points the one thing I'd say up
front is the biggest mistake I see to
your point on building features because
they're cool is teams build what they
think should be in the product and what
they think would be cool to be in the
product and at no point do they talk to
the user and try and understand what do
your users want and are you building
what they want and need it's really easy
to just keep building what you think is
cool and then those features never get
used and they get lost in the shuffle
and you end up with kind of a crowded
product on the other side of that so
strongly recommend like talk to your
users get feedback from them around what
they want because ultimately that's what
matters you're not building a product
for yourself you're building a product
for other people within that though we
did think about it in terms of so when
we're building a new feature is it a
feature or a product my general bias in
the mobile space is towards Slimmer
products and being okay having multiple
products that serve adjacent use cases I
think the mobile form factor has a lot
of benefits but it also has some
limitations and I think having a product
that for example has like eight
different features on a smartphone app
and like a 6-in screen it's very hard to
get users to understand all of those
features and effectively switch between
them and use them and I think maybe
having two or three products that have
two two or three features each could
actually deliver more value and you may
even get more financial value out of it
because you could better segment users
into the product that actually suits
their needs so we did think a lot about
that and we generally aired on the side
of less features and being more willing
to just build a net new product if we
thought there was demand there and then
we were actually doing features so we
went through that analysis and said this
should be a feature in the product two
ways we thought about it there which is
are we trying to increase arpo or are we
trying to increase retention and I would
say all of your features should fit into
one of those two buckets cuz I'm not
sure what the other rationale for
releasing a new feature is if you're not
going to increase RP retention that's a
great lens so then you have to think
about like what am I really trying to
achieve with that so we had some
features where we released and it was an
upsell and we said this is you know an
adjacent use case it helps solve the
same problem one example is in Robo
killer we integrated data broker removal
service and that was an upsell so we
sold you into the base subscription and
then we said do you also want this on
the other side was really successful a
really good way to increase RPO and it
made sense having it as a feature within
the product there are other things
you're going to release or features
you're going to release where it's more
about retention and engagement and I
think the strategies for how you develop
those products or those features sorry
and how you Market those to your user
bases are very different so having that
Clarity up front is this a retention
oriented or an R oriented feature I do
think is very important in thinking
about that kind of Market sizing both
for features that you're adding on to
and new apps or new lines of business
one of the things I know comes up a lot
in the industry is how many apps seem to
get stuck in this like 10 to 30 million
a year Revenue threshold how did you
think about hitting that ceiling like
why some apps hit the ceiling and then
why some apps don't and how to push
through that maybe not the answer
everyone's gonna want to hear here I
tend to think most apps will hit that
ceiling and it's actually very hard to
break through it so the way we tended to
think about it and the way I still think
about it today is more of accepting that
as a constraint for the mobile business
and then how do you architect around it
or how do you build a business given
that constraint and and I think there's
a couple reasons why that's just a real
constraint one is if you think about
like user acquisition at a very basic
level you're going to get organic users
people just coming to the App Store
searching for things and they find your
app as a result of it and download it
then you're going to do paid user
acquisition and go out and bring user
pull users into your app on the organic
side it's hard for any individual
developer to materially move the amount
of searches happen in the App Store like
that's a pretty static figure that's
relatively out of your control so all
you can do is increase your ranking for
those keywords and at some point you're
going to hit your enough top three
rankings you're going to get your
rankings and they're going to stop being
able to move and you're going to almost
like maximize your share of that organic
pie now not everyone always hits that
point but like there is a cap on the
organic side for most products and then
you get to the paid side and I think the
challenge there is most people similarly
hit a ceiling on the paid side because
mobile ltvs just aren't in the grand
scheme of things if you go to like other
markets like B2B SAS ltvs and mobile are
pretty low most people are operating
under $100 subscriber LTV so there's
only so much you can then pay to acquire
a subscriber and then basically what
happens is you're going to keep spending
and at some point your CAC is going to
reach that maximum and you can't spend
more unpaid without going unprofitable
so you decide to stop spending and then
when those two things happen that's when
you kind of hit a ceiling on your growth
and you can get you know call it single
digit growth on the other side of that
through LTV improvements testing
conversion rate improvements things like
that but you're not going to be doubling
in size on the other side of that I
think that's a very real constraint for
a lot of apps and a lot of mobile first
products though again the way we think
about it is that's why you see a lot of
portfolios where it's okay if you accept
that as a constraint the other way to
grow is to have multiple products and if
you have three $30 million products
that's just potentially as good and
maybe even better because of the
diversification benefit of having one
single $90 million Revenue product so I
do think it's a real constraint I don't
think it's a constraint on the ability
to build great mobile businesses though
and I actually think it could be an
opportunity if thought about the right
way yeah but an important thing to think
about especially for those who've raised
funding and kind of increased the bar of
success is that to understand this
eventuality is important and one of the
more interesting ideas on that paid
front that I've heard Eric suer gosh
probably like six or eight years ago
talked about how this idea that if there
is ultimately kind of a a limited ideal
customer profile for your app in a
limited pool of people especially
willing to pay whatever you know higher
price which a lot of apps are kind of
tending toward now there is a limited
pool of people who care enough to
subscribe to an app that does
XYZ and the more you spend and the more
you're willing to stretch your CAC the
faster you saturate that pool and you
still end up at that same eventuality so
if today you're growing at 200% and like
things you just feels like you can't
spend enough and you're just going so
fast you may just be rushing faster
toward that same Cliff not necess neily
kind of escaping the laws of
thermodynamics and the speed at which
you're currently going isn't necessarily
sustainable just because you seem to be
accelerating faster than other apps as
you've said and I'll reiterate like I
don't think this is universally true
there are going to be breakout products
like a dualingo but it's like those are
the exceptions that prove the rule that
there are just so many spaces that don't
have a big enough Tam don't have enough
kind of willing consumers to pay these
higher prices that make the return on
ads spin work that you are going to find
some ceiling and for some apps it
actually may be lower than that 10 to 30
million doll threshold for some apps it
may be a little higher and then you're
going to have those that break through
but kind of understanding those Dynamics
I think is super important in kind of
informing strategy how much you're
willing to spend how much you're willing
to stretch out your payback periods how
fast you're willing to invest that
revenue and things along those lines and
I actually think on that point one thing
to Think Through is actually think about
a lot of those exceptions like a dual
lingo even a Spotify is inherently
mobile first product a Common Thread I
see at least is they have big free user
bases or at least for a large part of
their life had very big free user bases
I say this as someone who has always
prioritized limited free user free usage
or free user basis I'm in favor of even
like hard pay walls in some examples but
you have to also accept when you're
doing that you are playing into the I'm
probably capping this 10 20 30 million
of Revenue there are not very
many paid only subscription products
outside of the streaming world that
really gain traction without that
substantial free user base that drives
adoption in community and brand yeah
that's a really good point how do you
think retention plays into all this
because for an app that does actually
have ridiculously good retention you can
still build a great business layering
those cohorts year after year after year
where even if you kind of max out the
number of users you can acquire if
you're actually
retaining a much higher percentage you
can still continue growing at high rates
but that's a challenge yeah I I do think
that's the path forward and I think
that's what you should be focused on is
like one of your most important signals
in your business is how do your
subscribers retain and what's that
average life cycle and you want to be
higher and longer as much as possible
but even there I think there's two
challenges coming back to why things cap
out one it comes back to LTV your
retention a very obviously an important
input to your LTV and in the mobile app
space like great retention is often like
on a blended basis across all your
durations 50% of subscribers every year
is like you're doing pretty well if
you're doing that but that also means
50% of your cohort is leaving at the end
of that year so that's one going to
impact your LTV like if you think about
B2B SAS they're at like you know
sometimes over 100% retention because
they're actually upselling that's a very
different world they're living in from
an LTV perspective and then two like
again if your incoming new users is flat
so your cohort size is flat and you're
turning out half of the cohorts every
year like you can only grow so much now
like higher retention is better these
are still recurring businesses and as
you get into years like two three four
five for a lot of these cohorts it's
actually much higher than 50% retention
is what you're seeing so you definitely
get a stacking benefit as you drag these
things out I do think you one way to
optimize that is to your earlier point
is like don't blow the doors off
marketing right away and like have one
giant cohort that's going to slowly at
trit over time be patient and bring in
more evenly sized cohorts over a
multi-year period and you can actually
potentially get much better recurring
revenue and like a much more evenly
spaced out renewal base across various
points on that renewal curve so you can
get really sticky bases of Revenue that
are good relative sizes to those new
users that are coming in
and then part of this whole topic around
like hitting these caps and the reason
folks think about these things is that
especially if you've you know taken any
amount of funding but even if you
haven't I think a lot of people are
thinking about the in eventuality of a
potential exit so then how an potential
exit come into play with these
challenges in scale what do you think
the range of potential outcomes exist
for subscription app today so the
outliers like dual lingo you can IPO
that's that's an awesome strategy if you
can execute on it and out setting that
one aside because I do think that's the
exception not the norm typically what
we'd see is there's three buyers of
these assets if you want an exit one is
you could sell to there are many
portfolio place in this space people who
are rolling up Diversified portfolios of
apps they're always willing to take a
look at things I think they're a very
willing seller probably your most
realistic seller theirs business is
buying and selling apps so they're
probably going to be more regimented on
valuation than some of your other buyers
because like their whole thing is they
have to get good Roi in every single
deal for their business model to work so
they're going to be pretty strict on
their valuations second is you can sell
to private Equity there are some small
scale private Equity players who are
interested in this space I think the key
there though is it's hard to sell them a
single app so if you're just a single
app developer you're probably looking at
the app rollup portfolios if you've
built a portfolio of app you can be be
able to hand off almost more of like a
business than a product to those private
Equity players and you can say hey I
have these three apps and I have a
Consolidated Tex stack behind it and
this is a great platform that you can go
out and add more products to that's a
story and like a narrative that can get
you into the kind of lower end of
private equity and get an exit there and
then lastly for certain apps I think
strategic buyers are very real like you
saw Under Armour what was that 5 10
years ago at this point did a buch of
Acquisitions in the space I think you
can see similar things where there's a
strategic who has a strong rationale for
wanting to buy your product that's
probably for any given product there's
going to be a handful of companies that
you'll know will make sense for that but
you can have an eye towards trying to
establish relationships or making
yourself visible to them to set up that
potential exit and then the last one I
always advis people also like I don't
think everyone has to exit per se Again
part of the benefit is these are
recurring businesses you can build up a
sticky renewal base and maybe the right
thing for you is to actually just at
some point shift a little bit more into
maintenance mode where if what you're
trying to do is spend more time on other
things you do that but you still take
your cash flow from maintaining a
product and continuing to provide the
value that those users thought they were
getting when they purchased the product
I mean I think like in the mobile app
space you could do that with a
reasonable time commitment that still
allows you to go do other things yeah I
want to step back to the Strategic buyer
it seems like we saw a lot more of this
early on I don't feel like I've seen as
much of this recently although maybe I'm
just not paying enough attention to the
m&a space but have you seen any kind of
strategic Acquisitions that you think
are interesting or do you see specific
categories and companies that might make
sense for these kind of strategic
purchases yeah I do think you can so
like actually the budgeting space as one
example rocket mortgage bought I think
was true bill at the time and now it's
rocket money um because for them that's
actually to the reason why we never
found the category attractive it's a
great customer acquisition funnel for
them of getting people into their
budgeting tool and then selling them
actual Financial products on the other
side of that so I think Financial
Services is definitely one where you can
continue to see that I think privacy
security is another area where you have
some big consumer Brands like the
Nortons of the world and the mcafe and
things like that where they could still
be interested in maybe increasing their
mobile presence or their mobile brand
those are the the two big ones that
stand out to me and they also think
health and wellness although to your
point I think that's one where we've
seen that fade recently and I generally
agree with your classification here
which is if you look back like 10 or 15
years mobile was this like exciting new
platform and and was like desktop versus
mobile I think we're kind of on the
other side of that where mobile is more
of a standard and just kind of baked
into everything everyone does and most
people have some degree of mobile and
desktop presence so I do think it's you
had Rush early on where it was like
every Big company felt like they had to
have a mobile play and they were using
m&a as a way to accomplish that and now
I think it actually is more tightly tied
to product fit and like does this
product make sense does it generate us
more revenue does it help lower our
customer acquisition cost not just like
mobile for the sake of mobile which you
got more of in you know 15 years ago
yeah and and two recent acquisitions
that I think point to that is both Under
arour And The Weather Channel selling to
Francisco Partners private Equity Firm
where both of those I would have guessed
you know had you asked me three years
ago who would buy something like that I
mean famously IBM actually bought the
Weather Channel and from what I
understand they still maintain the B2B
side of the weather business and then
Under Armour having bought my fitness
pal and a few others and a few others
and then they spun it out and now it's
landed at private equity it's like my
fitness pal kind of being a darling of
the health and wellness space it's like
if somebody was going to get a strategic
acquisition by a bigger player that's
one that I would have guessed would and
they didn't so those are I think two
data points showing yeah maybe the
Strategic acquisition space is limited
but then one other data point on the
other side is you know Z Davis acquired
L it recently that is in the health and
wellness space they're a big media
conglomerate
so it's like there are still
opportunities but it's just yeah it
seems very different in 2024 than it has
been yeah it's going to be a very small
Universe typically when we would do I
also worked on sales out of our
portfolio at IAC when we'd make buyers
list for most companies your strategic
buyers are like five to 10 potential and
then you have a list of like a 100
Financial buyers who could potentially
be interested in it and I think that's
going to stay true here where it's a
very small population potential
strategics and a much larger population
more financially motivated buyers yeah I
think few people listening to this
podcast don't have some inkling in the
back of their mind like an acquisition
or some kind of bigger liquidity event
would be an interesting Prospect in the
future and so kind of understanding
those dyn Dynamics I think is important
the other thing I'd advise is if that is
what you're optimizing for if that's
what you seriously want the end goal to
be build towards that goal don't just
assume it's going to happen like be
thoughtful around who is a potential
buyer what what can I do to make this
more interesting to that buyer or even
like if you haven't built a thing yet
and you want to build a thing to get
acquired like have that be part of your
selection criteria of what you're going
to build is what does the acquisition
pool look like for this thing and
therefore do I want to build it or not
that both from a prodct perspective and
then I'd also say from an operational
perspective the cleaner and more
professionalized your setup is the
easier it's going to be to find a buyer
for that buyers don't love messiness
they're already taking on a lot of Risk
by doing an upfront p for an uncertain
outcome on the other side anything you
could do to reduce that messiness for
them is great yeah any other advice on
kind of opening up those potential doors
strategic or PE I mean imagine like if
you're building toward a private Equity
exit and you think that's kind of the
maximum the optimal return Then building
something that's throwing off cash and
being more careful more disciplined with
spin being more disciplined with
expenses like showing that profitability
or the the opportunity for profitability
is something that is going to be way
more valued by private Equity again
maybe you shouldn't be building
exclusively this direction because we
know it's such a limited pool of
potential outcomes but if you are hoping
for strategic acquisition would you then
maybe be trying to build a more of a
brand or or have a unique take or any
advice on that spectrum of building
toward a hopeful exit yeah I do think
particularly if you're going to be going
to a financial buyer having a track
record that they can understand and
project out and say if I just do more of
that this is going to go well for me is
important so for example you've been
running unprofitably your entire life
and then you go to them and say but if
you buy this it's going to become
profitable like that's just a harder
Hill for them to get over as opposed to
saying look it's already been profitable
for the last three years just keep doing
XYZ and this is going to go well for you
that's a much easier narrative to sell
them so I do think being to a point
where you are either already profitable
or your union economics are clearly
going to drive profitability in the
future even if like right now it's not
immediately profitable that is great for
the financial buyers it does probably
matter a bit less for the Strategic
buyers and I do think like brand and
maybe even just like the size of your
user base matters more for strategics I
think for example strategics will always
Place more value on free users and
Community than a financial buyer will so
there are differences there
in terms of what they're kind of value
yeah well this has been fascinating I
mean picking your brain having been in
this space for so long and looking at so
many apps over such a long period of
time both I didn't even think about that
you would be working on selling parts of
iac's portfolio while also potentially
acquiring others so you've been both on
the buy side and the S side of this in a
really interesting way and across many
years of kind of ups and downs of the
industry so yeah that was
really fascinating thanks for sharing
all those insights so I did want to dive
into the more kind of tactical side of
things that you you learned running as a
GM of it translate and robok killer the
first one there is how to think about
user acquisition LTV CAC paybacks I mean
it's just such a big hairy mess and yeah
I mean it's actually something we're
thinking a lot about at Revenue cat you
we now do have some LTV predictions
we're kind of teas are are going to be
adding those to our experiments feature
but It's Tricky and like we've actually
been really careful and turtl and had a
lot of like thought around how we build
these products because it's really easy
to just throw a pltv stat out there but
like what does it actually mean can I
trust it can I buy against it is a
really important question so so yeah I'd
love to hear kind of your thoughts
around how to think about these metrics
LTV is heart particularly if you're in
the early days what I advise people to
do is think more about your range of
possible outcomes because the reality is
you have very limited data that data is
not going to tell you a perfect story on
the other side of it and say with 100%
confidence this cohort LTV is going to
be X you're getting a directional
estimate at best so the way we do it in
the early days of a product and what I
advise people we work with to do is run
a range of scenarios and say you know
plus or minus 20% and maybe 5%
increments what are my Poss possible
ltvs assign some probabilities to them
come up with your best estimate start
making decisions and acting on that and
then just go back and check it every
month or two months as you're getting
that retention data in start validating
and what you could hopefully start doing
is if you start with hey I have six
possible ltvs then I'm giving some
waiting to each of them then you can get
it down to four ltvs over time and then
two then three or you know however that
goes and eventually get to a more
precise LTV estimate that you're going
to have but like you're going to need
mature
just from a scale perspective to get to
a relatively precise LTV like you need
multiple years of data realistically to
be able to reliably predict that so
that's okay in my mind you just have to
again like know where you're at in that
cycle are you in the less certain and
therefore you need to be more flexible
and dynamic or are you in the more
certain side of your cycle where you're
more mature and you can kind of have
more of a singular Target of how you
think about things and maybe this is one
of those things you need to like kind of
pick a point in time and say what's my
LTV going to be at one year what's my
LTV going to be at two years and kind of
more cash flow prediction because LTV is
such a a loaded term and that I I don't
even like in the subscription app
industry in that I've seen with my own
app I launched it my weather my dinky
little like side project weather app
launched it seven years ago and still to
this day I've retained like 10 15% of
the original cohort who who bought it s
years ago and so trying to estimate that
into the future and then saying my
seven-year LTV is going to be X you
can't actually calculate the average
lifetime value of a user because it can
go decades into the future I mean
there's products like Netflix I
subscribed to Netflix as a DVD customer
in 200 what 4 or something you know 2001
and then I transitioned from DVDs to
their streaming service and I've been a
monthly paid C customer for close to 20
years now I think that's where the rest
of the industry is going like a weather
app whether it's on AR glasses 10 years
from now you know I'm probably going to
have users that have 20y year lifetime
30e lifetimes even my simple little
dinky side project weather app I'm
ranting here but it's like I don't like
LTV as a term because of that because
nobody really you can't actually
estimate an average life time value of a
user but you need some Metric to buy
against for cash flow and that's where
actually you know this is something Dan
he is a colleague of mine at Revenue cat
formerly a colleague of yours at teltech
at rubber killer and he brought to our
charge this metric called realized LTV
the way I think about it is like day x
realized LTV because in the revenue
catch chart you can actually pick like
how much revenue have I made on this
cohort at 30 days at 90 days at a year
and and you there's a little drop down
that you can select it and to me that's
just such a more helpful way to think
about quote unquote lifetime value is
more like pick different time points and
do those calculations toward like what's
the range of expected Revenue at 12
months at 24 months at 36 months because
that it just feels like that's so much
more helpful than thinking of it as just
like this is all the money I'm ever
going to make from this cohort and
here's the line I'm drawing in this hand
totally agree a couple thoughts there
one we always did Caper ltvs so to your
point maybe calling them lifetimes is
not actually a Accurate Way of framing
that but we typically would cap them at
a certain number of years for two
reasons one is like you have to get paid
back at some point so like you have to
care about your payback period if you're
buying against a 20-year LTV maybe
you're not even making a profit here 15
and like that's not a super functional
business model to be managing and then
two is not to get like too Finance nerd
on people there's a time value of money
so like a dollar in 20 years is worth
less than a dollar today so even if
you're still having some of your cohort
renewing and paying you in 20 years if
you discount that back to what is that
actually Worth to me today it may be
very minimal and therefore not actually
worth baking into your LTV so we did cap
it I would advise people to cap it and
then also to your point I I think coming
back to like where are you at in your
maturity life cycle you also need to
think about payback periods so like
typically what we say is like when
you're earlier in your life cycle you
can't be waiting 12 months to make a
profit on a cohort you need to have
tighter payback Windows because you just
don't have a lot of cash on hand to
spend when you're later in your life and
you have more money in the bank you
could potentially think about you know
if maybe you started a 2-year LTV maybe
you start expanding that to a three or
fouryear LTV and being okay having a 12
plus month payback period I again I
think you can play with those ever as
time goes on but I would definitely
advise capping your LTV it just will
make your life simpler and easier and
it's a at worst you're being
conservative and like that's not a
terrible thing to do and that I would
think about payback periods as almost
like a separate and distinct metric from
your LTB to CAC or your row ass but then
how does that work out practically like
in what time frames would you cap your
LTV like would you look at a particular
app and say based on the cash flow of
this app we need RADS at day 90 and so
we're going to predict I mean would you
call that a predicted I mean again it's
like you're not predicting lifetime
value so you're predicting cash flow
within 90 days not an actual lifetime
how did you do those specific kind of
projections like what's our cash flow
going to be at nine months 90 days at at
nine months at 12 months how did you
think about that tactically yeah so we
did have an in-house proprietary system
forecasting ltvs again we benefited from
being more mature so we had a ton of
data on all of our products where if we
got you know an initial renewal point or
initial Che renewal points from a given
cohort we could pretty reliably predict
out then what the next 20 would look
like from there and also what you see is
typically in those first couple renewals
is actually where you see the bulk of
your turn and then it starts flatlining
after that so we were able to pretty
reliably predict those and then we manag
on LTV to CAC predominantly I think of
them as two separate ways I think you
either have a primary filter of what's
my payback period And basically I'm at a
stage in my company's life cycle where I
need to make my money back either in in
the first month or in the first three
months and therefore that's the primary
thing I'm optimizing for and then
secondarily I'm looking at LTV to CAC to
understand what that looks like because
what you may find is okay I need to get
paid back same month but then what I see
is I have a crazy high LTV to CAC so
once I solve my like cash liquidity
problem and I can extend that payback
period I now know that I can spend a lot
more money and still have a healthy LTV
a CA so then you can think about like
what do you need to do from a business
perspective to unlock growth which is
find liquidity somehow right
alternatively later in life you're going
to be probably more focused on LTV to
CAC and say okay I have a threshold has
to be above the certain LTV to CAC and
your payback period is almost more of
like a sanity check on the side of okay
if I if I'm targeting a two or three x
LTV to CAC I want to know how long I'm
getting it's taking to get me paid back
but that's probably not the thing that's
driving your business decisions it's
just more of a nice to know on the side
yeah did you have any particular moments
where specific new ad spend or even
specific new ad creatives or new prices
or any specific changes that you saw
break your model did you have moments
where like oh we you know ramped up
spend on meta and everything looked
great ltvs were amazing and then like
you do the 3mon look back you're like oh
crap like we were 25% under what we
predicted like this cohort sucked like
we shouldn't keep acquiring these users
in that way you have any specific
examples like that a lot a short answer
so it's definitely a thing a couple
quick examples so on price testing that
was always an issue we generally so we
generally skewed either annual or
monthly subscriptions or some
combination of the two you can pretty
easily get a sense for what's going to
happen to your monthly subscriber
retention when you're running a price
test if you're willing to wait you know
a little bit of time you're obviously
not going to have data on what happens
to your annual subscribers retention
though when you're making that decision
like no one's reasonably waiting over a
year to make a call on a price test so
you have to make some simplifying
assumptions there we typically what we
would do is look at the impact on
monthly subscriber retention and say in
theory the annual retention impact
should approximate what we're seeing in
monthly subscribers that was not always
true though and in particular if like
one is clearly your primary plan and one
is your secondary plan so it's like a
7030 split between those durations they
won't actually always work the same so
we often with price tests particularly
if they were overweight annual
subscriptions sometimes we'd make calls
and then you'd see those cohorts come in
a year plus later and you'd be like ah
like that maybe wasn't the right call
unfortunately or you're very pleasantly
surprised and it was a better call than
you even anticipated I don't have a
great solution for avoiding that what I
typically advise people is you're going
to look at your ab test results and just
sensitize it to say if retention comes
in 10% worse does it change my answer of
if I should roll this that or not if it
comes in 20% worse does it change my
answer and then make a decision based on
your relative Comfort level there like
if you have only have a 5% buffer on
retention before this price test winner
is no longer a winner maybe don't roll
that one out or maybe be more cautious
about how you roll that one out if
retention can go down by 50% and that
thing's still a winner like close your
eyes and roll it out you're going to be
fine with any reasonable outcomes there
so I I would say sensitize price test is
a big learning we've had particularly
when your annual subscriptions and then
new marketing channels is definitely a
thing I think a couple implications of
that are like when you're ramping up on
or you're launching a new channel or
you're ramping up on a new channel be a
little conservative like don't go full
bore my experience is actual performance
almost always contracts from that
initial predicted performance when
you're doing a new channel because a
combination of retention is probably
going to come in a little bit worse than
you were expecting that's just life and
like those first handful of users you
acquire are almost always the cheapest
users you're going to acquire and like
eventually it's going to start getting
more expensive and eventually it's going
to start Contracting on you so like
patience is important there and give it
a little bit to play out before you just
like say I want to pour gas on the fire
I do see sometimes people are a little
too quick to in their minds pour gas on
a fire that may not be real so I do
think you have to think about that but
it's I think just something you have to
factor into your decision- making and
it's just a reality of the world we live
in yeah how much did you think about the
impact and how much did you see the
impact of price on those longer
retention periods so I feel like it's a
bit of a trend and I've talked about it
a lot on the podcast I actually talked
about it on the episode just before this
one that these much higher subscription
prices do work really well to get that
payback quickly like this shift toward
annual subscriptions and then more
specifically the shift toward higher
priced annual subscriptions is closing
the loop on being able to get that like
sday return on ad spin for some apps
that seem to be doing really well and
finding the right creatives and stuff
like that but then just inherently the
higher your price there's going to be
some impact on CH and how do you think
about balancing those things and what
did you see in the data as you looked at
some of these bigger cohorts in the
Mosaic portfolio retention as a general
rule decreases as price increases so you
should think of those as inversely
correlated basic logic holds if
someone's paying more for something
they're more sensitive to the value
they're getting out of it so we did see
that on the whole it is definitely not a
onetoone relationship meaning you're
going to net get LTV wins most of the
time assuming conversion rates line up
so we typically see if you increase
price 10% maybe retention comes down by
a couple percent for example and then
it's also not one size fits so some
products saw it more than others and
particularly like I always advocate for
being really honest with yourself around
like what your product does and the
value it provides I think there are a
lot of very successful and very
profitable and great products in the
mobile space that provide a somewhat
thin layer of value and I don't say that
with like any negativity associated with
it like they provide a distinct value
but it's thin and like you they built a
great business around that but like be
realistic about that and know that
there's then probably a lower ceiling on
how much you can charge for that value
there are other products that are like
dual lingo or language learning is
potentially an example there where it's
like there's a really deep Corpus of
content underlying them like you're
truly teaching someone a skill a thing
that they pay in the real world maybe
thousands of dollars to go somewhere to
learn you have more Price Power there so
like be honest with yourself about how
much value you're providing there aren't
necessarily wrong answers there the most
important thing is just be honest with
yourself yeah and were there specific
like leading indicators that you would
look at to understand how price
especially on annuals because again so
much of the industry is Shifting toward
annual to get those earlier paybacks but
then it lengthens the feedback loop like
were you feeding into the the payback
model and the retention model and the ab
test results early turning off auto
renew engagement data like what were the
factors that helped you get a window
into the future performance when the
real data was going to be 12 months out
yeah so a couple of things so like I
said if you have a shorter term
subscription like a monthly subscription
seeing the impact on that retention from
a similar price increase and being able
to extrapolate it out similarly if
you've raised price before and you said
okay last time I raised an annual price
10% this is what happened to retention
using that as a indicator of what could
happen in the future works also if you
have a free trial trial to paid
conversion is typically going to be a
leading indicator of retention on the
other side so if you're seeing a drop in
trial to paid you're probably going to
see a drop in retention not necess one
to one again but it's a leading
indicator we did not see a lot of
success using early cancellation rates
as a predictor of churn we just didn't
uh we did a lot of testing around it
only a fraction of users actually cancel
early what you see is you get a lot of
cancellations like right around the
renewal point when they're kind of
getting those emails letting them know
that it's coming up so we did not end up
we used it it was not a particularly
valuable data point for us I think
engagement can be a valuable data point
if you have the clarity and the tracking
and like the good data around those
features so if you have like a key
action the user is going to take in your
app or a key feature that they need to
use being able to track that and making
sure people are still doing that and
still doing that on a recurring basis I
think can be a good indicator is
definitely a good indicator that one
gets trickier to feed back into do
something like an LTV algorithm though
so that's the I think the challenge
there often times what I see is that's
almost used as like a
thing that sits on the side where you
have your LTV algorithm and then you're
looking at your cohorts and are they
doing that action and then you're making
some in your head like mental adjustment
to what your LTV algorithm is saying
because it's just hard to feed those
back in no that makes a lot of sense so
it's like if the LTV is saying this but
we see usage retention differing from
past cohorts then I should buy 10% then
we should discount that LTV 10% I mean
yeah something I've talked about before
like in a in a talk I gave and we have
talked about on the podcast but I loved
your Insight on Are there specific
things that are going to be the most
meaningful to track to get that sense
like do you need to pick one specific
core user flow one specific key value
that the app delivers is there like I
mean I guess every app's going to have
their own thing any tips on like picking
that user action that's going to most
strongly correlate with retention which
then is going to help more more strongly
correlate with LTV and your financial
projections yes we tried to have one or
two Maxs for every product I think if
you have like seven then you just you're
creating noise and the actual signal is
getting lost in that noise so really
think about like the one or two key
things so for example like robokiller it
was actually less about what was the
user doing it was more about are they
actually getting spam calls and are we
blocking calls on their behalf and
trying to understand like the passive
use
yeah like it are we providing the value
that the user came to us for and that
that may not be dependent on an action
they've taken so that's the lens I would
suggest applying is it's more about the
is your product providing the value that
may be because we have another uh app
called table call which is a call
recorder the value there is recording a
call that has to be a user action so
there it is a user action did they
actually record a call but again the
verbal Cod example it it's not actually
a user action you're looking for it's
just a thing that happens in their
environment and you're confirming that
they are getting spam calls we are
blocking them on their behalf and
therefore they're getting value out of
it and actually even there like we had
two metrics of are the getting spam
calls now we blocking them and then also
did we get one wrong and for us that was
actually the big flag for us when we
needed to do something proactive about
retention if we saw we got something
wrong for a user that was highly
correlated with churn so then we needed
to remediate that in some way shape or
form probably a good exercise for any
app that hasn't already done this this
is do some user surveys do some user
interviews pump all your reviews into
chat GPT and figure out like why are
people actually paying for the app like
what really is the value and I like that
one that robokiller example is so good
is that people aren't paying to interact
with the app they're paying to not
interact with the app they're paying for
the app to sit in the background and
block those calls at time s an inverse
correlation between how much you used
robok killer and how happy you were with
the product where it's like if you were
using it a lot you actually probably
were a less satisfied user because you
were trying to do all these like tweaks
and coming in to check things did we
really get it right like our happiest
users kind of forgot we were installed
on their phone in a good way even in
that case I mean this is maybe a rabbit
hole to the current conversation but
were there ways in which the user did
see robok killer taking action like
would it pop up a notification like
robok killer block this call or you
still have to kind of reinforce the
value that you're delivering like hey we
blocked 50 calls for you this week alone
and reminding people that how much value
they're they're actually getting
delivered when it's just sitting there
in the background passively delivering
value it was a challenge for us for a
couple technical reasons namely around
Apple limitations or around the data you
do and don't have on a user level and
then also our own privacy layer we had
put on top of that but like think of
creative ways around that so one thing
we did is we generally de anonymized
like all day data cuz we thought that
was the right thing to do so instead of
giving you necessar personalized stats
we would give you stats across the whole
user base of we've lock this many
millions of calls this month for our
users so still being able to demonstrate
like we are doing things we are
providing value even if we can't
perfectly tie that to like you as an
individual user all right so we've kind
of been dancing around the acquisition
side of things in talking about LTV and
and measuring your LTV and like figuring
out how your users are engaging with the
value of your product but then you do
have to go out and acquire those users
so how did you think about marketing and
customer acquisition costs and kind of
keeping that in check especially in
relation to LTV yeah we did think about
the world in organic vers paid or two
lenses we put on it and then I think you
can think about your ca then both from a
blended perspective so basically
accounting for your organic traction and
a paid only perspective and I would
strongly recommend that you look at both
of those me
because like there are apps that you'll
see that are unprofitable if you look at
them on a paidon basis but profitable on
a blended basis which is great and that
may be the right decision for your app
but that probably means you don't have a
lot of growth ahead of you the more you
spend on paid the more negative that's
going to go and it's just going to drag
down your margins so that's why it's
important to understand it because it
influences what you can do going forward
but looking at how paid impacts the
Blended because for some apps there is a
little bit of a network effect where if
you spend more it's also going to juice
your organic so if you have any kind of
like Network effect spending more maybe
does balance out but for but to the
point we've been making throughout this
whole podcast is like that's probably
the exception and for most apps you're
not going to have enough of a network
effect some of the things that do come
into play here though is that you know
as you spend more and bring in more
users and get more reviews you do push
yourself up the search results so that's
like an important aspect but to your
point earlier it's like you also cap
that out it's like you know if if you
can't spend more than a million dollars
a month maybe you Peak at number three
result for the the most valuable keyword
and you just can't push it beyond that
so kind of watching the interplay
between paid and Blended is probably how
you determine where that's going to land
and I do think that's a very real effect
in the mobile app ecosystem I think it
has diminishing returns though so I
think early in your life there is a very
strong correlation between paid traction
and organic growth where as you drive
more paid downloads you can absolutely
increase your organic installs along the
way at some point you will start to see
that Flatline though and like you'll get
diminishing returns and for every paid
install you're getting you're getting a
smaller and smaller fraction of an
incremental organic install as a result
so again like understanding that
trade-off and where you are on that
curve is important because then what
you're thinking about is like is all
that matters my LTV to cack on that
incremental of paid spend or should I
actually be discounting that or maybe
applying a premium to that LTV to CAC
because I know I'm getting some
incremental organic benefit on the other
side so I I do think that's very embor I
also think to the organic side of things
like ASO is very critical like I think
it is based on some of the data I've
seen it's like over 50% of installs go
to come through search and go to one of
the top three rankings on search so it
is really critical that you if you're
going to launch a product understand
what relevant keywords for your product
understand what is your ability to rank
on those keywords this comes back to
like when you're thinking about a
category in the competition like if you
say I need to rank on this keyword and
the first three keywords are like
hundred million doll companies with
massive budgets like that's probably a
concern that you need to think through
and think through how you're going to
handle that so you're saying I shouldn't
build a weather
app well it seems to be a category
that's done well regardless yeah but I I
do think that's real where it's like you
have to be really thoughtful about what
are the keywords that matter and then
measure where you're at on those
keywords because what you want to
understand is one like what's your
growth opportunity and how realistic is
that you can achieve that but then also
like that tells you where you are in the
curve of diminishing returns on your
organic lift because of paid spend if
you're already ranking one two three on
the keywords you care about there's only
so much more upside you're going to get
from your more paid spend other than
just like the economics on that paid
spend so I think that being keyword
aware is very important I think this
goes to a kind of broader strategy
though is that I think any app needs to
have some leverage in user acquisition
I've talked about this a lot and we're
talking about it through these two
specific lenses ASO and paid spend I do
think there's maybe 10 other potential
lenses to look at it through Al rails
being a really famous example it's like
they didn't have to rely as much on
Apple search although they got featured
a ton they proba did get a ton of apple
search but like they had a user
acquisition advantage in SEO on the web
if you go search for any Trail and
they're going to show up I think there
are advantages you can build outside of
ASO and paid spend but you need to
understand what that Advantage is and
what you're building toward and for a
lot of apps and especially again like
you said at the very beginning of the
podcast if you're trying to build a new
category that people aren't searching
for it is a really hard uphill battle
because you got to figure out something
outside of the app store that's going to
drive people whether it's like you know
Tik Tock organic whether it's SEO
whether it's you know some advantage in
paid spend that you're building
something unique but it is hard to go
build a real business in the app store
around something that people aren't
searching for and I think a lot of
people discount just how much some of
these bigger apps benefited from like
the CMS the head spaces the my fitness
Pals lose it famously I mean they were
at the top result for decade plus they
were one of the earliest calorie
counting apps and rode that ASO wave
into this massive business that they are
today I think that's discounted a lot or
not kind of fully understood when you're
trying to compete in that calorie
counting space or other spaces the
incumbents have this advantage in that
search that is nearly impossible to
break in 2024 so like what can you bring
to the space and leverage in user
acquisition outside of ASO or paid if
that's going to be really hard to
compete in or do you have some advantage
in paid because ASO is going to be
really tough to crack in these bigger
categories agree with all that I think
so we treated things like content and
SEO as organic in our view so like ASO
was kind of one leg of the organic stool
but totally agree you can get real user
acquisition through other like so
content was definitely one that worked
for us our best example was for robok
killer we were the biggest app in the
space and in the US so therefore we had
a lot of data on spam calls and texts in
the US and we started publishing reports
and working with reporters to basically
help them report on the issue to say
here's how many spam calls Americans are
getting every month here's how it's
growing we worked with the FCC and the
FTC to get them data too because they
didn't have great data and all of this
so we found that we had this proprietary
data set people were interested in
talking about it and it wasn't a direct
we talked to this reporter and we're
going to get a bunch of users but like
when you start
accumulating multiple Wall Street
Journal articles that reference you and
like multiple Financial Times articles
that reference you and you're getting
placements on cable news and things like
that that starts building a brand and
organic Halo and you could absolutely
Drive significant user acquisition
through that so we saw a lot of success
with that to the extent you can
replicate it like definitely do that and
then Community is another one that I
think could be very impactful if you can
build a community I think it's really
hard but I think it can be very
impactful and I think maybe not the most
traditional sense of it like dual lingo
I think that was a big part of their
early growth was they made it largely
free it was very gamified it became this
thing that you talked about you were
doing you did it visibly on like the
subway to work people saw you doing it
and they created this like real brand
awareness by building a very large
community of unmonetized users and then
they figured out the monetization in a
much more meaningful way on the other
side of that so I do think what you
think about breakout stories
I actually think the most common Trend
between them is they have found some
very meaningful channel of organic
acquisition outside of App Store search
and that's really what's helped them
break through that ceiling we were
talking about before yeah yeah totally
makes sense so I kind of took us down
multiple R holes but back to like
brass's tactics on how to think about
customer acquisition costs what are the
specific things you're looking at there
so we talked about kind of Blended and
paid CAC but then what are some of the
the formulas and other things you look
at there I think it's important to look
at look look at it across your funnel
there's a couple different like
intersection points you could think
about things like generally what we see
is you are thinking about a cost per
install a cost per free trial or cost
per subscriber I would pick one of those
as your primary metric and that should
tie to your monetization strategy so for
example if you're a free app that's
mostly advertising driven you probably
want to think about a CPI um because you
don't have a free trial or subscribers
so therefore those aren't relevant
metrics to you if you don't use free
trials cost per free trial isn't super
relevant but if you just go into direct
subscriptions think about that if you
use free trials it may benefit you to
think about a cost per free trial
because that's a more Dynamic quicker
metric you don't have to wait seven days
for them to convert out of the free
trial to figure out what your cost per
subscriber is so just think about it on
a cost per trial basis obviously you
have to make sure that your LTV matches
whatever you're using as the denominator
for your cost but I think about like
where in the funnel do you want to
measure your acquisition cost is
important and like I said then you think
about it as paid and Blended and then
even within paid think about Channel
specific acquisition costs so
understanding is meta more expensive
than Google or Tik Tok for example and
then understanding where can you pull
levers and increase your spend on the
other side of those and then I think
more broadly tactically where a lot of
paid spend has trended in the mobile
space is large like blackbox algorithms
if you think of Google and meta are the
two biggest platforms for able to spend
on ASA as well but like both Google and
meta basically set a bid in a budget and
like that's the degree of control you
have over those platforms so what
becomes a huge lever and I'm certainly
not the first person to say this is
creative is a very big lever and you
need to be really focused on it and so a
couple things we say there is like
always be testing creatives you should
always have some like if you think about
the creatives in your campaign and those
different structures or how you do this
but like there should be some percent
that are experimental that are unproven
and you're just always putting new ones
out there to see what resonates and then
two one tactical tip I give people a lot
is rotate designers on your project what
you often unsurprisingly like everyone
has no matter what your profession is
like your own distinct style certain
Engineers have a certain way that they
like code things and like the way their
mind works Finance Guy background my
financial models had a very consistent
like theme and flow to them in terms of
like how my brain worked and how that
translated into a model all designers a
pretty like unique and personal like
theme are the things that they like to
lean into and if you keep using the same
designer what you find is like you get
in this trap of incremental improvements
where what you're really doing is you're
changing 5% or 10% of a thing to see if
it works a little bit better and
sometimes it's actually better is to
bring in a new designer and just be like
hey like this is the product go wild
with it like obviously you got have
brand guidelines around it and it's got
to be relatively consistent but like
actually try something wholesale new and
see how how that performs so we tried to
get in a rotation of we'd actually for
our creative teams rotate them across
products so you'd work on this product
for a couple months and then you'd
rotate to another product for a couple
of months and that way got us more
diversity of the types of creatives that
were flowing through there and then so
we could pick the winners out and start
understanding okay well like this style
is resonating let's do more of that
style as opposed to the style almost
being like a fixed thing because it's
just the designer style now this is a
huge can of worms and we do need to wrap
up so I'll ask for the top tips and the
uh two to three minute answer but you
got to ride the wave of ATT at mosaic so
we've been talking CAC and measuring
your paid spend the question people will
be shouting back is like okay cool those
those calculations are great but like
any top tips on on actually putting pen
to paper and measuring these things or
or keyboard to spreadsheet as it were
how do you actually
meaningfully measure both paid spend
return and organic return the quickest
answer is run multiple analyses and look
at the aggregate of those analyses so
like the way I I think about in the
postat world is like you still have mmps
they're still going to give you some
degree of a breakdown of your
acquisition by channels take that at
face value understand what that says
then also do a blended analysis and say
like what does my Blended look like am I
still okay with Blended similarly just
do like paid vers organic and say there
maybe some mixup between channels so on
a holistic paid basis with the MMP is
telling me do I feel good about that and
start like aggregating across those I
don't think anyone can rely on like One
Singular dashboard I yearn for the days
of preat where I had like a looker
report that I fully trusted and like I
just knew that like this specific Geo
campaign on Google was doing this but
like that those days are gone and like
you have to accept that they're gone in
my view at least so you do that and then
also think about
like
operationally how and when you launch
and or scale things so what I mean by
that is like if you say okay we don't do
any paid spend now and we going to
launch on Google meta and Tik Tok don't
do all three at once just launch on
Google and then understand okay like all
we've changed is we're now spending on
Google what's the impact of that get
Google to a steady state and then say
okay now I'm going to launch on meta and
now you're you have a new Baseline and
all you've done is change one thing if
you launch all three at once it's going
to be very hard to understand and the
relative performance of each and like
what's going on there so always think
about Inc like doing things very
incrementally and same thing if you
already launched and you want to start
changing bids and budgets change like
one bid give it a month see what happens
then change another bid and you have to
give yourself time to establish
baselines so that you can do that like
incrementality analysis of I made a
change and now what am I seeing in my
aggregate numbers as a result of that
yeah that's super helpful and probably
the most helpful thing is for folks to
just hear
it's hard yeah it's hard like you're
always kind of guessing and at the end
of the day like I ground myself in
Blended performance which is like
because like that's your p&l is
inherently a blended mix of everything
you're doing and so like and at the end
of the day your p&l is what has to make
sense what has to work so like that
should be your North Star and like your
grounding light of does the Blended make
sense and if the answer is no like you
got to go figure that out and then as
long as the Blended is making sense then
attempt to better understand the D under
there but like always be grounded in the
Blended has to make sense yeah well I
think it's a a great place to wrap up I
know people would be hoping for a magic
answer I feel like I get asked this all
the time like how do I measure like
which MMP do I use and and the answer is
like it's just hard and everybody's got
to figure it out tell Apple to reverse
their
change well I've been pushing hard on uh
improving scan I think Apple well what
is it called now I don't even remember
the new acronym for it but uh I don't
think Apple even has to reverse at to
get back to better they just need to
better incentivize the industry to use
whatever it is now not ski network but
whatever it is we could get to a much
better place on on reporting if if they
would provide the tools and and be a
little less precious about an anonymity
because like at scale some tiny amount
of potential for user data leaking like
the way they built their tools is is
very Ivory Tower like like zero personal
data can leak that's just not how the
real world works because if data on two
or five users is potentially able to be
de anonymized at scale that's not it
doesn't matter like nobody's going to
bother deaning those handful of users
when there's millions of data points
flowing through the system I'm still
hopeful I mean obviously Apple's never
going to put the at Genie back in the
model so my hope is is actually that
they just continue iterating on those
tools to make it better and more
deterministic over time by improving
those systems which I think there's tons
ahead room for them to do they've just
been very slow to do it it's also a
great opportunity for the marketing
channels themselves to start
differentiating like I here recently
meta is starting to pull away in terms
of relative performance because they've
invested a lot more in how to operate in
an post at world
and so I think what you could start
seeing is some marketing platforms
invest more in that than others and
that's where more of the dollar start
flowing to all right well this has been
so much fun but as we're wrapping up
anything you wanted to share I know
you're working on some new projects and
anything you wanted to share about those
yeah I've started a new Venture it's
called the app shop it's myself and some
old colleagues from the Mosaic group the
gist of what we're doing is taking all
of our lessons and experiences and and
learnings from all of those years
building Mosaic and offering up to other
companies playing in the space we love
the mobile app ecosystem we want to see
it grow we're largely doing consulting
and agency Services can help with
marketing monetization and product
development if anyone's interested we
we'd love for you to reach out our
website's the app shop.io awesome well
Patrick thanks so much for joining me it
was so much fun thank
you thanks so much for listening if you
have a minute please leave a review in
your favorite podcast player you can
also stop by chat. sub club.com to to
join our private community
[Music]